Okay, so in this video,
we're going to cover
another tool called a
source selection criteria.
Now, source selection criteria was
considered a tool and technique of plan
resource management and it's basically
determining what vendors
are going to work for us.
What kind of vendors are we going to reach
out to, right?
So you're determining the type of vendor
and basically what's selection criteria?
They have to meet a minimum criteria in
order to be considered.
So, as a very, very simple example,
again, let's think of something simple.
You're doing some work in your house.
Are you doing some remodeling work in your
house?
Well, there's thousands of vendors out
there.
There's thousands and thousands of
contractors.
Which one are you going to choose?
You are not going to reach out to big,
huge, large construction firms to do some
remodeling work in your house normally,
right?
you would probably reach
out to small local contractors,
small local vendors in order
to do some remodeling work.
Using big, huge, large construction firms
is just overkill.
And plus most of these large construction
firms are not going to do a small job,
like just some remodeling work in your
house.
So you're going to have your own selection
criteria.
And that's really what this refers to what
vendors are going to work for us.
They have to meet a
minimum criteria in order for
them to, in order for
us to reach out to them.
And generally, you do
this before you submit an
RFP, before you submit
a request for a proposal.
So just some very simple examples here,
lowest cost vendor, right?
Some organizations will say, we have to go
with the lowest cost vendor.
So low cost vendor or lowest cost
qualified vendor.
And then there's a whole selection
criteria on what you mean by qualified.
And then sometimes it's just based on
qualification certification, right?
The vendor has to have at least this
minimum certification or this minimum
qualification.
Otherwise, we're not going to reach out to
them, such as, for example, they have to
be a six sigma or they have to be CMI
level three.
Otherwise, we're not going to reach out to
them.
Could be also based on their size and
experience, right?
So we want a large vendor.
Or we don't want a large
vendor, we only want a small
vendor, just like again, when
you're remodeling your house.
so you're not going to reach out to big,
huge, large construction firms, right?
So you're going to reach out to a small
company.
Also, based on certain classifications,
right, so those of you that work for the
US government or any of the US government
agencies or contracting companies,
right, you may have come across this
classification called
veteran-owned small business.
And there's other classifications as well,
minority-owned small business,
woman-owned small business, and many other
classifications as well.
A lot of government agencies use this as a
minimum criteria.
You have to be a veteran-owned small
business in order to bid on this contract.
So this is a project that is a set-aside
for a veteran-owned small business or a
woman-owned small business or a
minority-owned small business.
So you have to meet this minimum criteria
in order to bid on the contract.
If your organization does not fall into
that classification, there's no point in
even applying, even bidding on that
contract.
So there's many, many different criteria
that you and your organization will be
considering, right, when you're trying
to determine which vendor to use, right?
Could be based on the management approach,
based on past performance, right?
So based on that, since we're going with,
say, a small vendor, we
want some references.
So, you know, the vendors have to supply
minimum of three
references and so and so forth.
So there's many things that you might be
considering.
These are just a handful, like,
just some of the more common criteria,
some of the more common considerations.
But that's what the source selection
criteria first do.
They have to meet a minimum criteria.
Now, along with this, there are
two other terms, and these fall
under what's known as
non-competitive forms of procurement.
So remember, we're trying to determine
what vendor are we going to reach out to?
Right?
Well, you might come across this time
called a sole source.
Soul source basically means that there is
only one vendor that we can reach out to,
either because they are
a monopoly or because
of some exclusive rights that they have.
Right, so a monopoly
basically means they're
the only vendor that can perform the work.
They're the only organisation.
No one else can perform this work.
That's what monopoly obviously refers to.
So if there's the only
vendor that can perform the
work, then obviously we
don't have a choice, right?
Which vendor we're going to reach out to?
Well, we can only reach out to this one
vendor.
Or it could be because they have exclusive
rights, such as patents.
Right, they've got some patents or
copyrights, right?
So they have exclusive rights to this
particular work.
So we have to reach out to them.
Or it could also be because of some prior
relationship that we have with them.
So, a prior relationship,
such as some of you
may have come across
a sole source contract.
So this is a sole source contract for two
years or a five-year sole source contract,
which basically gives this vendor
exclusive rights to any work that,
or any relevant work that we need to
outsource.
So we have to outsource it to this sole
source contractor.
So we have this prior
relationship with them,
or in this case, this
is this prior contract.
They have exclusive rights.
Another term that's very similar is
something called a single source.
A single source refers to preferred
vendor.
It refers to a preferred vendor.
So we need to outsource this work.
We have a preferred vendor.
We prefer to go out to this one vendor.
There may be a couple of preferred
vendors.
We're going to reach out to these
preferred vendors.
However, there's no obligation.
There's still many contractors
out there, many vendors
out there, that we can still
reach out to if we wanted.
They're a preferred vendor, but there is
no obligation for us to reach out to them.
So that's the basic difference then
between sole source and single source.
With sole source, we have no option.
There's only one vendor.
We have to reach out to this one vendor.
With a single source, there
may be one or two preferred
vendors, but there's no
obligation to reach out to them.
Okay.